[
 {
   "question": "What 1923 comedy features the classic shot of Harold Lloyd dangling from a clock face?",
   "answer": "Safety Last! "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the capital of Australia?",
   "answer": "Canberra "
 },
 {
   "question": "What boxing movie won the 1976 Best Picture Oscar?",
   "answer": "Rocky "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who holds the record for most Best Actor Oscar wins for his performances in My Left Foot, There Will Be Blood, and Lincoln?",
   "answer": "Daniel Day-Lewis "
 },
 {
   "question": "What filmmaker holds the record for most nominations for the Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay?",
   "answer": "Woody Allen "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who won the Academy Award for Best Original Score for his work on 2015’s The Hateful Eight?",
   "answer": "Ennio Morricone "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the capital of Nigeria?",
   "answer": "Abuja "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Black Maria film studio, where early shorts such as Fred Ott’s Sneeze and Prof Welton’s Boxing Cats were filmed, was the creation of what American inventor?",
   "answer": "Thomas Edison  "
 },
 {
   "question": "What 1922 film about an Inuit family is one of the earliest feature length documentaries?",
   "answer": "Nanook of the North "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed 1998’s The Thin Blue Line, a documentary which helped to overturn a wrongful murder conviction?",
   "answer": "Errol Morris "
 },
 {
   "question": "What musician was the subject of DA Pennebaker’s 1967 documentary Don’t Look Back?",
   "answer": "Bob Dylan "
 },
 {
   "question": "From what Italian movie did the word ‘paparazzi’ originate?",
   "answer": "La Dolce Vita "
 },
 {
   "question": "What 1972 gangster film was based on a novel by Mario Puzo?",
   "answer": "The Godfather "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1991 thriller The Silence of the Lambs?",
   "answer": "Jonathan Demme "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Raymond Chandler character did Humphrey Bogart play in the 1946 film noir The Big Sleep?",
   "answer": "Philip Marlowe  "
 },
 {
   "question": "What 1996 Danny Boyle film was based on a novel by Irvine Welsh?",
   "answer": "Trainspotting "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Ken Kesey novel, and Milos Forman film, features the characters Randle McMurphy, Nurse Ratched, and “Chief” Bromden?",
   "answer": "One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest "
 },
 {
   "question": "What 12 minute western of 1903 is considered the first film to use cross-cutting (using editing to show simultaneous action in different locations), and ends with a famous shot of a cowboy shooting at the camera?",
   "answer": "The Great Train Robbery "
 },
 {
   "question": "What 1925 Soviet film by Eisenstein features the famous Odessa Steps sequence?",
   "answer": "Battleship Potemkin "
 },
 {
   "question": "Clint Eastwood (as Dirty Harry) said his famous line ‘Go ahead, make my day’ in which Dirty Harry movie?",
   "answer": "Sudden Impact "
 },
 {
   "question": "In what film does Lauren Bacall deliver the line, ‘You know how to whistle don’t you, Steve? You just put your lips together and blow.’?",
   "answer": "To Have and Have Not "
 },
 {
   "question": "In what 1932 film is the line ‘We accept her, one of us, gooble gobble’ chanted?",
   "answer": "Freaks "
 },
 {
   "question": "Name the 2016 documentary about the US prison system, directed by Ava DuVernay, which gets its title from the amendment to the US constitution that abolished slavery.",
   "answer": "13th "
 },
 {
   "question": "Of what 1997 superhero franchise movie did Roger Ebert write that Uma Thurman ‘suggests plants *can* have multiple orgasms’?",
   "answer": "Batman & Robin "
 },
 {
   "question": "According to Peter Bradshaw, ‘Travolta not only incinerates what is left of his own reputation, but takes someone else down with him: Forest Whitaker’ in what L Ron Hubbard-inspired sci-fi of 2000?",
   "answer": "Battlefield Earth "
 },
 {
   "question": "What three films were winners of the 'big five' Oscars (best picture, best director, best actor, best actress, best screenplay)?",
   "answer": "It Happened One Night (1934), One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest (1975), The Silence of the Lambs (1991)"
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the capital of the United Arab Emirates?",
   "answer": "Abu Dhabi "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the chemical symbol for tungsten?",
   "answer": "W "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the chemical symbol for silver?",
   "answer": "Ag "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the chemical symbol for gold?",
   "answer": "Au "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Ancient Greek comic playwright wrote The Wasps, The Birds, and The Frogs?",
   "answer": "Aristophanes "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Ancient Greek tragedian is famous for writing Oedipus Rex?",
   "answer": "Sophocles "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Ancient Greek tragedian is famous for writing Medea?",
   "answer": "Euripedes "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Roman poet is famous for writing Metamorpheses?",
   "answer": "Ovid "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Roman poet Ovid is famous for writing what collection of stories of transformations?",
   "answer": "Metamorpheses "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Fighting Temeraire is an 1839 painting by what artist?",
   "answer": "JMW Turner "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Toilet of Venus, also known as The Rokeby Venus, is a 17th century painting by what artist?",
   "answer": "Diego Velázquez "
 },
 {
   "question": "Bacchus and Ariadne is a painting by which Italian Renaissance painter, whose name has become associated with red hair?",
   "answer": "Titian "
 },
 {
   "question": "Starry Night is an 1889 painting by what artist?",
   "answer": "Vincent van Gogh "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Kiss is an early 20th century painting by what Austrian symbolist artist?",
   "answer": "Gustav Klimt "
 },
 {
   "question": "Water Lily Pond is an 1899 painting by what artist?",
   "answer": "Claude Monet "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Garden of Earthly Delights is a tryptich painting by what master of the Early Netherlandish school?",
   "answer": "Heironymous Bosch "
 },
 {
   "question": "Girl with a Pearl Earring is a 17th century painting by what Dutch artist?",
   "answer": "Johannes Vermeer "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Scream is an 1893 painting by what Norwegian artist?",
   "answer": "Edvard Munch "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Wanderer Above a Sea of Mist is an 1818 painting by what German Romantic painter?",
   "answer": "Caspar David Friedrich "
 },
 {
   "question": "Syn-propanethial S-oxide is an irritant released during what activity?",
   "answer": "Cutting onions "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Luncheon on the Grass, depicting a female nude with two fully dressed men, is an 1863 painting by what French Modernist artist?",
   "answer": "Édouard Manet "
 },
 {
   "question": "American Gothic is a 1930 painting by what American artist?",
   "answer": "Grant Wood "
 },
 {
   "question": "Saturn Devouring His Son is one of the 'Black Paintings' by what Spanish Romantic painter?",
   "answer": "Francisco Goya "
 },
 {
   "question": "Sefl-Portrait with Bandaged Ear is an 1889 painting by what Dutch Post-Impressionist?",
   "answer": "Vincent van Gogh "
 },
 {
   "question": "What does USB stand for?",
   "answer": "Universal serial bus "
 },
 {
   "question": "The name of what branch of mathematics derives from 'al-jabr', originally an Arabic term for bonesetting?",
   "answer": "Algebra "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the word radar short for?",
   "answer": "Radio detection and ranging "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the word laser short for?",
   "answer": "Light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the word sonar short for?",
   "answer": "Sound (or sonic) navigation and ranging "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the word scuba short for?",
   "answer": "Self-contained underwater breathing apparatus "
 },
 {
   "question": "What is the chemical symbol for mercury?",
   "answer": "Hg "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Hunters in the Snow (Winter) is a 1565 painting by what artist?",
   "answer": "Pieter Bruegel the Elder "
 },
 {
   "question": "The Death of Marat is a 1793 painting by what French artist?",
   "answer": "Jacques-Louis David "
 },
 {
   "question": "The School of Athens is an early 16th century fresco by what Italian renaissance artist?",
   "answer": "Raphael "
 },
 {
   "question": "Two Tahitian Women is an 1899 painting by what French artist?",
   "answer": "Paul Gauguin "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Ancient Greek philosopher wrote The Republic around 380 BCE?",
   "answer": "Plato "
 },
 {
   "question": "What two German philosophers wrote the 1848 pamphlet The Communist Manifesto?",
   "answer": "Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Russian chemist is credited with publishing the first modern periodic table of elements in 1869?",
   "answer": "Dmitri Mendeleev "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who invented vulcanised rubber in 1839?",
   "answer": "Charles Goodyear "
 },
 {
   "question": "What did Charles Goodyear invent in 1839?",
   "answer": "Vulcanised rubber "
 },
 {
   "question": "What Scottish-born inventor was granted a patent for the telephone in 1876?",
   "answer": "Alexander Graham Bell "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who invented the phonograph in 1877?",
   "answer": "Thomas Edison  "
 },
 {
   "question": "What German astronomer's three laws of planetary motion describe the orbits of planets?",
   "answer": "Johannes Kepler"
 },
 {
   "question": "Which of Einstein's theories includes the postulate that the speed of light is absolute?",
   "answer": "The special theory of relativity"
 },
 {
   "question": "Which of Einstein's theories predicts gravitational lensing?",
   "answer": "The general theory of relativity "
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1975 film Jeanne Dielman, 23 quai du Commerce, 1080 Bruxelles?",
   "answer": "Chantal Akerman"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 2000 film In the Mood For Love?",
   "answer": "Wong Kar Wai"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1963 Italian avant-garde film 8½?",
   "answer": "Federico Fellini"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the Soviet science fiction films Solaris (1972) and Stalker (1979)?",
   "answer": "Andrei Tarkovsky"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1987 Iranian film Where is the Friend's House?",
   "answer": "Abbas Kiarostami"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1957 Swedish films The Seventh Seal and Wild Strawberries?",
   "answer": "Ingmar Bergman"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1959 epic film Ben-Hur?",
   "answer": "William Wyler"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1988 novel The Alchemist?",
   "answer": "Paolo Coelho"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1951 novel The Catcher in the Rye?",
   "answer": "JD Salinger"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1980 Italian novel The Name of the Rose?",
   "answer": "Umberto Eco"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1902 children's novel The Tale of Peter Rabbit?",
   "answer": "Beatrix Potter"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who directed the 1948 Italian film The Bicycle Thieves?",
   "answer": "Vittorio De Sica"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1960 Southern Gothic novel To Kill a Mockingbird?",
   "answer": "Harper Lee"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1936 self-help book How to Win Friends and Influence People?",
   "answer": "Dale Carnegie"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1925 novel The Great Gatsby?",
   "answer": "F Scott Fitzgerald"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1961 children's novel James and the Giant Peach?",
   "answer": "Roald Dahl"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1988 science book A Brief History of Tine?",
   "answer": "Stephen Hawking"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1813 romance novel Pride and Prejudice?",
   "answer": "Jane Austen"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1963 children's book Where the Wild Things Are?",
   "answer": "Maurice Sendak"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1965 science fiction novel Dune?",
   "answer": "Frank Herbert"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1939 novel The Grapes of Wrath?",
   "answer": "John Steinbeck"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1979 comic science fiction novel The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Universe?",
   "answer": "Douglas Adams"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1994 autobiography Long Walk to Freedom?",
   "answer": "Nelson Mandela"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who wrote the 1952 novella The Old Man and the Sea?",
   "answer": "Ernest Hemingway"
 },
 {
   "question": "What Polish-born physicist was awarded the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for the discovery of radium and polonium?",
   "answer": "Marie Curie"
 },
 {
   "question": "What politician won the Novel Peace Prize in 1991, and defended the Burmese military against allegations of genocide at the Hague in 2019?",
   "answer": "Aung San Suu Kyi"
 },
 {
   "question": "Who won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1945 for his discovery of the Exclusion Principle, which is named for him?",
   "answer": " Wolfgang Pauli"
 }
]